
[
  {
    "question": "Regarding the following diseases which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) Omenn syndrome, an autosomal recessive severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID), is due to mutation in RAG-1 & RAG-2 which result in deficiency in V(D)J recombination.\n(B) X-SCID (or SCID-X1) is due to mutation in Jak3 which is a critical signal molecule of receptors for various cytokines such as IL-2, IL-4, IL-7, IL-9 & IL-15.\n(C) X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA), an immunodeficiency with very low amount of Ig, is due to mutation of Btk, a signal molecule downstream of BCR.\n(D) Bare lymphocyte syndromes are caused by mutations that lead to an absence of MHC molecules.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Omenn syndrome, an autosomal recessive severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID), is due to mutation in RAG-1 & RAG-2 which result in deficiency in V(D)J recombination.",
      "B": "(B) X-SCID (or SCID-X1) is due to mutation in Jak3 which is a critical signal molecule of receptors for various cytokines such as IL-2, IL-4, IL-7, IL-9 & IL-15.",
      "C": "(C) X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA), an immunodeficiency with very low amount of Ig, is due to mutation of Btk, a signal molecule downstream of BCR.",
      "D": "(D) Bare lymphocyte syndromes are caused by mutations that lead to an absence of MHC molecules."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "(A) 正確。Omenn syndrome 為體染色體隱性 SCID,因為RAG1、RAG2 的突變，使得原始(pro)淋巴球無法變成前驅(pre)淋巴球，造成免疫缺陷。\n(B) 錯誤。X-SCID 為人類 X 染色體上 IL2RG 基因突變，影響其編碼的γC。IL-2 細胞介素家族(包含 IL-2、4、7、9、15、21)的受體皆需要 γC，其中 IL-7 和IL-15 缺乏會造成T細胞和 NK 細胞無法發育、B細胞發育正常但會因缺乏 T細胞協助活化而功能異常。而 SCID 中有一類為 JAK3 基因突變(如選項所述)，由於 JAK3 為γC 的訊息傳遞分子，造成免疫缺乏的機制相同，因此此 種AR-SCID 的免疫表現型與 X-SCID 相同而無法區分(同為T-B+ NK-,但 B 細胞功能異常)。\n(C) 正確。X性聯無γ免疫球蛋白血症(XLA,又稱Bruton agammaglobulinemia) 為Btk(Bruton's tyrosine kinase)基因發生突變,導致患者周邊血液缺乏B細 胞且無γ免疫球蛋白或低下。Btk是Tec-family kinases 的一員,負責傳遞 Pre-BCR 傳下來的訊息,缺乏Btk 功能使B細胞發育被抑制在前驅B細胞，因此 在B細胞的發育中扮演重要角色。\n(D) 正確。Bare lymphocyte syndrome 為細胞表面 MHC 不表現,可分為第一、二 型,分別對應MHC I和MHC II 的缺乏。前者主要源自 TAP1/TAP2 或 Tapasin 的突變。\n［出自考古第1題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding ITAM & ITIM which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) ITAM is a motif that can transduce activating signals.\n(B) ITAM & ITIM are only found in immunoreceptors of the adaptive immune cells, such as T & B cells.\n(C) Cell response is determined by the summation of activation and inhibitory signals transduced by ITAM and ITIM.\n(D) There are 2 ITAM motifs in a BCR.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) ITAM is a motif that can transduce activating signals.",
      "B": "(B) ITAM & ITIM are only found in immunoreceptors of the adaptive immune cells, such as T & B cells.",
      "C": "(C) Cell response is determined by the summation of activation and inhibitory signals transduced by ITAM and ITIM.",
      "D": "(D) There are 2 ITAM motifs in a BCR."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "(A) 正確。ITAM 和 ITIM 分別是傳遞活化和抑制訊號的模體(motif)。\n(B) 錯誤。TCR 和BCR 的次單元都包含ITAM 以進行訊號傳導,此外其他免疫系 統的受體也會包含 ITAM 與ITIM,如NK的各種受體上也包含 ITIM 和ITAM 以辨識其他細胞;NK、巨噬細胞和嗜中性球上的 FcyRIII (CD16)上連結 Fcy chain 或 TCR 上也有的 ζ鏈,使NK細胞進行 ADCC,而後兩者則促進吞 噬與抗體結合的病原體。\n(C) 正確。\n(D) 正確。BCR 結合的 Igα 和 Igβ 上各包含一個ITAM。\n［出自考古第2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the structure of antibody which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) There is one variable domain and three constant domains in a heavy chain of an antibody.\n(B) An antibody has two antigen binding sites and one Fc domain.\n(C) Hinge region of an antibody is a molecular ball-and-socket joint that is very flexible.\n(D) Carbohydrate is attached to CΗ3 domain of the heavy chain.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) There is one variable domain and three constant domains in a heavy chain of an antibody.",
      "B": "(B) An antibody has two antigen binding sites and one Fc domain.",
      "C": "(C) Hinge region of an antibody is a molecular ball-and-socket joint that is very flexible.",
      "D": "(D) Carbohydrate is attached to CΗ3 domain of the heavy chain."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(A) 正確。重鏈由一個變異區(V)跟三個恆定區(C)構成。\n(B) 正確。一個抗體可以被木瓜酵素(papain)切成三塊:兩個 Fab 與一個 Fc。\n(C) 正確。樞紐(hinge)類似球窩關節(ball-and socket joint),可以改變抗體兩 臂的角度,以便結合分開一段距離的抗原,如細菌細胞壁多醣體的重複單 元;或是使抗體可以和免疫蛋白作用,以調控免疫反應。\n(D) 錯誤。醣類修飾是在 CΗ2 功能區。\n［出自考古第3題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding development of T & B lymphocytes, which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) During lymphocyte development, TCR and BCR undergo gene rearrangement or re-combination.\n(B) The gene rearrangement is a random event because the rearranged TCR or BCR can recognized both self and non-self antigens.\n(C) Negative selection of both immature T & B cells occurs in the bone marrow.\n(D) Following development, mature T & B cells will migrate to spleen & lymph nodes.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) During lymphocyte development, TCR and BCR undergo gene rearrangement or re-combination.",
      "B": "(B) The gene rearrangement is a random event because the rearranged TCR or BCR can recognized both self and non-self antigens.",
      "C": "(C) Negative selection of both immature T & B cells occurs in the bone marrow.",
      "D": "(D) Following development, mature T & B cells will migrate to spleen & lymph nodes."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(C)T細胞的負選擇(negative selection)主要發生在胸線的皮質與髓質。\n［出自考古第4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diversity of immunoglobulin repertoire is determined by the following mechanisms except:\n(A) Junctional diversity\n(B) Combinatorial diversity\n(C) Somatic hypermutation\n(D) Isotype switching",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Junctional diversity",
      "B": "(B) Combinatorial diversity",
      "C": "(C) Somatic hypermutation",
      "D": "(D) Isotype switching"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D)抗體的不同類型(isotype)的差異在於重鏈的組成與修飾,而這不會改變抗 原結合位的構造,故不會對抗體的組譜(repertoire)產生影響。\n［出自考古第5題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding IgD & IgM which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) The antigenicity of IgD & IgM in one mature B cell is different.\n(B)(選項亡佚)\n(C)(選項亡佚)\n(D)(選項亡佚)",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) The antigenicity of IgD & IgM in one mature B cell is different.",
      "B": "(B)(選項亡佚)",
      "C": "(C)(選項亡佚)",
      "D": "(D)(選項亡佚)"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A) \"Antigenicity” describes the ability of a foreign material (antigen) to bind to, or interact with, the products of the final cell-mediated response such as B-cell or T-cell receptors.(通常是用來描述抗原而非受體)\n推測原選項應是指抗原特異性(antigenic specificity),而IgM 和 IgD 具有相 同的抗原特異性,只差在具有不同的重鏈(Fc region)\n［出自考古第6題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding cytokines, which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) The JAK-STAT pathway is the major signaling pathway transduced by cytokine receptors.\n(B) Different cytokines may have the same biological effects.\n(C) Most of the cytokines are constantly expressed without stimulation.\n(D) One cytokine can regulate the production of other cytokines.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) The JAK-STAT pathway is the major signaling pathway transduced by cytokine receptors.",
      "B": "(B) Different cytokines may have the same biological effects.",
      "C": "(C) Most of the cytokines are constantly expressed without stimulation.",
      "D": "(D) One cytokine can regulate the production of other cytokines."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(A) 正確。細胞介素在免疫細胞最常活化的就是 JAK-STAT 途徑。\n(B) 正確。此性質為細胞介素的冗餘性(redundancy)。\n(C) 錯誤。大部分的細胞介素都是有刺激才會產生的。\n(D) 正確。細胞介素之間會互相調控,形成梯瀑式(cascade)的放大效果。\n［出自考古第7題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding monoclonal antibodies, which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) It is produced by hybridoma cells that is fusion between naive B cells & myeloma, a tumor cell line.\n(B) It is possible to make a monoclonal antibody against antibodies.\n(C) Monoclonal antibodies can be used as a drug to treat patients with autoimmune disease like rheumatoid arthritis.\n(D) You can use label toxin or isotopes to monoclonal antibodies to target tumors.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) It is produced by hybridoma cells that is fusion between naive B cells & myeloma, a tumor cell line.",
      "B": "(B) It is possible to make a monoclonal antibody against antibodies.",
      "C": "(C) Monoclonal antibodies can be used as a drug to treat patients with autoimmune disease like rheumatoid arthritis.",
      "D": "(D) You can use label toxin or isotopes to monoclonal antibodies to target tumors."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A)錯誤。透過融合漿細胞與癌細胞(如骨髓瘤細胞),可以形成融合瘤 (hybridoma),會同時具有腫瘤細胞不斷分裂和漿細胞製造抗體的能力。初 始B細胞本身不製造抗體,因此融合為融合瘤後依然無法產生抗體。\n(B) 正確。例如 Omalizumab 透過結合人類 IgE 來達到治療過敏性氣喘。\n(C) 正確。Adalimumab 是一種重組過的 IgG,可以治療類風濕性關節炎 (rheumatoid arthritis)。\n(D) 正確。見下圖。\n［出自考古第8題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding variable domain of an antibody, which statement is NOT correct?\n(A) There are three hypervariable domains in one light chain or heavy chain variable domain.\n(B) The hypervariable domain is called complementary determining region of CDR.\n(C) Antigen binding site is determined by 3 CDRs of either light chain or heavy chain.\n(D) CDR3 is the most diverse of all CDRs because it is encoded by combined VJ or VDJ gene segments.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) There are three hypervariable domains in one light chain or heavy chain variable domain.",
      "B": "(B) The hypervariable domain is called complementary determining region of CDR.",
      "C": "(C) Antigen binding site is determined by 3 CDRs of either light chain or heavy chain.",
      "D": "(D) CDR3 is the most diverse of all CDRs because it is encoded by combined VJ or VDJ gene segments."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(C)錯誤。抗原結合位是由重鏈的3個互補性決定區(CDR)和輕鏈的3個互補 性決定區共同決定的,此性質稱為組合多樣性(combinational diversity)。\n［出自考古第9題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is C3 convertase?\n(A) C3BbB\n(B) C4b2b\n(C) C3(H2O)Bb\n(D) NOD",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) C3BbB",
      "B": "(B) C4b2b",
      "C": "(C) C3(H2O)Bb",
      "D": "(D) NOD"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "［出自考古第1題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is not involved in innate immunity?\n(A) Cathelicidin\n(B) Commensal bacteria\n(C) T-cell receptor\n(D) C-type lectin receptor",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Cathelicidin",
      "B": "(B) Commensal bacteria",
      "C": "(C) T-cell receptor",
      "D": "(D) C-type lectin receptor"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(A) Cathelicidin 是巨噬細胞(macrophage)和嗜中性球(neutrophil)內的一種抗 微生物肽(AMPs),對先天免疫反應很重要,作用於皮膚中角質細胞 (keratinocyte)或肺、腸中上皮細胞的感染。\n(B)共生細菌(commensal bacteria)可以藉由競爭養分和空間以防禦其他微生物 入侵,即生物學屏障。\n(C)TCR 出現在T細胞上,參與後天免疫反應。\n(D) C-type lectin receptor (CLR)為細胞膜上的模式辨認受體(PRRs)家族中的 一種,可以辨識醣類。\n［出自考古第2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is not the event during inflammation?\n(A) decrease in vascular diameter\n(B) cytokine production by macrophage\n(C) extravasation of neutrophils\n(D) blood clotting",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) decrease in vascular diameter",
      "B": "(B) cytokine production by macrophage",
      "C": "(C) extravasation of neutrophils",
      "D": "(D) blood clotting"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A)發炎時,血管直徑應「增加」。\n［出自考古第3題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is the property of (A) TD antigen (B) TI-1 antigen (C) TI-2 antigen (D) None?\n1. Activates B cells by cross-linking BCR and co-stimulatory signals from dendritic cell\n2. Induces polyclonal antibodies at high concentration, but specific antibody at low con-centration",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) TD antigen",
      "B": "(B) TI-1 antigen",
      "C": "(C) TI-2 antigen",
      "D": "(D) None"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "1-2. 1. TI-2 抗原的特色是有重複的片段,如多醣的莢膜(capsule),而B 細胞 (B-1 細胞或是 MZB)可以辨識並產生 IgM 對抗,若樹突細胞介入,其會 分泌BAFF 使B細胞進行類型轉換,產生 IgG。\n［出自考古第1-2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the property of human immunoglobulin?\n(A) IgM (B) IgD (C) IgG (D) IgA (E) IgE\n3. Transported by 2 molecules of FcRn across the placenta\n4. Dimer from predominates in secretion across epithelia",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) IgM",
      "B": "(B) IgD",
      "C": "(C) IgG",
      "D": "(D) IgA",
      "E": "(E) IgE"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "3-4. 3. IgG 為血液中最主要的免疫球蛋白,幾乎全身都有。可藉由胎盤上兩分子 的運輸蛋白 FcRn,運送一分子 IgG 進入胎兒,提供保護力。次級免疫反應 產生的主要抗體。\n4. 二聚體 IgA 主要分布在上皮細胞表面(epithelial surface),因為這些地方 缺少來自血漿的補體與吞噬細胞,所以 IgA 主要是以中和作用 (neutralization)來抵抗外來病原體。但是在淋巴結、脾臟的漿細胞分泌出 的 IgA 是單體形式(monomer),主要分布在胞外空間(extracellular space)和血液中。此外此兩種不同形式的IgA與亞型(subclass)相關:在 腸道分泌的二聚體 IgA 主要是IgA2,腸道中 IgA1: IgA2 = 2:3;單體 IgA 主要是 IgA1,在組織液或血液中的比例 IgA1 : IgA2 = 10 : 1。\n［出自考古第3-4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following tumors is involved in (A) T-cell tumor (B) B-cell tumor (C) Both T and B-cell tumor (D) Neither of them?\n5. Mantle cell lymphoma\n6. Multiple myeloma\n7. Sézary syndrome",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) T-cell tumor",
      "B": "(B) B-cell tumor",
      "C": "(C) Both T and B-cell tumor",
      "D": "(D) Neither of them"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "5-7. 5. 外套區(mantle zone)指周圍淋巴器官中生發中心(GC)外圍未活化B細 胞(resting B cell) 所在的區域,而 Mantle cell lymphoma 為這些 B細胞的 不正常增生,屬於B細胞腫瘤。\n6. 多發性骨髓瘤(multiple myeloma)為漿細胞(plasma cell)增生的惡性疾 病,絕大多數會分泌單株γ免疫球蛋白,故屬於B細胞腫瘤。\n7. Sézary syndrome 為皮膚 T 細胞淋巴癌(cutaneous T-cell lymphoma)的 aggressive form,經常影響皮膚導致皮膚損傷或紅疹。與蕈狀肉芽腫 (mycosis fungoides)同為最常見的皮膚T細胞淋巴癌亞型。(參考題目: 102 - 2醫檢臨床血液學#35)\n複習:B細胞腫瘤和T細胞腫瘤\n［出自考古第5-7題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following defects affects (A) T cell development only (B) B cell development only (C) Both B and T cell development (D) Neither B nor T cell development?\n8. DiGeorge syndrome\n9. X-linked agammaglobulinemia\n10. RAG deficiency",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) T cell development only",
      "B": "(B) B cell development only",
      "C": "(C) Both B and T cell development",
      "D": "(D) Neither B nor T cell development"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "8-10. 8. DiGeorge syndrome 是缺乏胸腺,因此T細胞無法順利發育。\n9. X性聯無γ免疫球蛋白血症(XLA,又稱Bruton agammaglobulinemia)為 Btk (Bruton's tyrosine kinase)基因發生突變,導致患者周邊血液缺乏B細 胞且無γ免疫球蛋白或低下。Btk是Tec-family kinases 的一員,負責傳遞 Pre-BCR 傳下來的訊息,缺乏 Btk 功能使 B 細胞發育被抑制在前驅B細 胞,因此在B細胞的發育中扮演重要角色。\n10.RAG1/2 是 BCR 和 TCR 基因重組必備的 DNA 重組酶,缺乏 RAG 會無法 製造出正常的BCR 跟TCR。\n複習:B細胞與T細胞的疾病\n［出自考古第8-10題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following statement are correct?(複選題)\n(A) T cell receptors are generated through somatic recombination.\n(B) The T cell repertoire encompasses a very large degree of diversity.\n(C) T cell receptors are secreted after activation.\n(D) The variable region of T cell receptors contains complementarity-determining regions.\n(E) T cell receptors are composed of two polypeptide chains.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) T cell receptors are generated through somatic recombination.",
      "B": "(B) The T cell repertoire encompasses a very large degree of diversity.",
      "C": "(C) T cell receptors are secreted after activation.",
      "D": "(D) The variable region of T cell receptors contains complementarity-determining regions.",
      "E": "(E) T cell receptors are composed of two polypeptide chains."
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "D",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(A)正確。體細胞重組(somatic recombination)在 TCR 和免疫球蛋白上都有發生; 而體細胞高度變異(SHM,somatic hypermutation)只發生在免疫球蛋白上。\n(B) 正確,T細胞和B細胞的組譜(repertoire)都有很高的多樣性。\n(C) 就算遇到抗原,TCR 也不會被分泌出來。\n(D) 正確,TCR 由含有3個互補性決定區(CDR)的Vα和含有3個互補性決定區 的Vβ 共同組成抗原結合部位。\n(E) 正確,TCR 和Ig 的Fab 相似,由α鏈、β鏈兩條分子量相近的多肽鏈平行構成 異質二聚體多肽,兩鏈之間以雙硫鍵鍵結。\n［出自考古第1題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "In regard to antigen presentation, MHC Class I molecules usually present peptide derived from ______ whereas MHC class II molecules usually present peptides from ______.\n(A) MIIC; self proteins\n(B) phagolysosome; proteasome\n(C) intracellular cytosolic sources; endosome/lysosome\n(D) CLIP; HLA-DM",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) MIIC; self proteins",
      "B": "(B) phagolysosome; proteasome",
      "C": "(C) intracellular cytosolic sources; endosome/lysosome",
      "D": "(D) CLIP; HLA-DM"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(C)以下簡述 MHC I/II 途徑:\n(1) MHCI途徑:細胞內在的抗原在細胞質內經蛋白酶體(proteasome)降解, 進入內質網後與膜上的 MHCI結合,再送到細胞表面呈現。\n(2) MHC II 途徑:外來抗原經吞噬後形成吞噬小體(phagosome),與溶酶體 (lysosome)結合形成吞噬溶酶體(phagolysosome),在裡面被降解成小 片段。小片段再與從內質體運送來的 MHC II 結合,並送到細胞表面呈現。\n(D) MHC II 還在內質網時,會與 CLIP(一種短肽)結合,保護其不與內質網內的 抗原作用。\n［出自考古第2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match the molecule or domains of molecules in Column A to what it binds in Column B.\nColumn A\nColumn B\na. α1 & β1 domains\n1. MHC Class I associated peptide\nb. β2 microglobulin\n2. CD4\nc. β2 domain of MHC Class II\n3. MHC Class I α chain\nd. α1 & α2 domain of MHC Class I\n4. MHC Class II associated peptide",
    "options": {
      "A": "a-4, b-2, c-3, d-1",
      "B": "a-4, b-2, c-1, d-3",
      "C": "a-1, b-2, c-4, d-3",
      "D": "a-1, b-3, c-4, d-2",
      "E": "a-3, b-1, c-2, d-4"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "［出自考古第3題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match the term in Column A with its description in Column B\nColumn A\nColumn B\na. invariant chain\n1. present peptide to CD8 T cells\nb. MHC Class I\n2. one of the soluble MHC-associated chain that is highly conserved\nc. MHC Class II\n3. transports MHC molecules to endocytic vesicle\nd. β2 microglobulin\n4. present peptide to CD4 T cells",
    "options": {
      "A": "a-3, b-1, c-4, d-2",
      "B": "a-3, b-4, c-1, d-2",
      "C": "a-2, b-1, c-4, d-3",
      "D": "a-2, b-4, c-1, d-3",
      "E": "a-1, b-2, c-3, d-4"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "4. a. Invariant chain(簡稱 Ii 或 CD74)會與新生的 MHC II 結合,然後Ii會被切斷, 留下一段叫做 CLIP 的短肽鏈,而 CLIP 可以在 MHC II 的運輸途中保護 MHC II 的結合位,避免 MHCII 與其他不是抗原呈現對象的肽鏈結合。因此,選項3的 敘述「transports MHC molecules to endocytic vesicle」最為相關。\n［出自考古第4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct for T cell priming?(複選題)\n(A) It occurs in primary lymphoid organs.\n(B) It transforms naive T cells into differentiated effector T cells.\n(C) It is the first stage of a primary adaptive immune response.\n(D) It requires interaction between naive T cells and antigen-presenting cells.\n(E) It can occur in lymph nodes, Peyer's patches and the tonsils.",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) It occurs in primary lymphoid organs.",
      "B": "(B) It transforms naive T cells into differentiated effector T cells.",
      "C": "(C) It is the first stage of a primary adaptive immune response.",
      "D": "(D) It requires interaction between naive T cells and antigen-presenting cells.",
      "E": "(E) It can occur in lymph nodes, Peyer's patches and the tonsils."
    },
    "answer": [
      "B",
      "C",
      "D",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "5. 樹突細胞(APC之一)移動到達淋巴結後製造 CCL19,吸引初始 T 細胞(naive T cell),並呈現抗原予初始T細胞,此即稱為T細胞的初打(priming),可刺激其後 續分化(proliferate)為作用 T細胞(effector T cell)。\n(A)應為「次級淋巴器官」。\n［出自考古第5題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match the T-cell type in Column A with the correct description in Column B\nColumn A\nColumn B\na. $T_{reg}$\n(1) help basophils, eosinophils & B cells respond to parasitic infections\nb. CD4 $T_{H1}$ cells\n(2) facilitate neutrophil response to extracellular bacterial infections\nc. CD4 $T_{H2}$ cells\n(3) suppress effector CD4 & CD8 T cell function\nd. CD4 $T_{H17}$ cells\n(4) differentiate under the influence of IL-12 & IFN-γ\ne. CD4 $T_{FH}$ cells\n(5) induce apoptosis of target cells\nf. CD8 T cells\n(6) help B cells become activated, produce IgG & induces antibodies class switch",
    "options": {
      "A": "a-3, b-4, c-1, d-2, e-6, f-5",
      "B": "a-3, b-4, c-1, d-2, e-5, f-6",
      "C": "a-3, b-4, c-1, d-5, e-6, f-2",
      "D": "a-3, b-4, c-2, d-1, e-6, f-5",
      "E": "a-3, b-4, c-2, d-1, e-5, f-6"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "6. \n［出自考古第6題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the host encounters pathogens, the dendritic cells in the infection site respond by producing cytokines. Cytokines produced by dendritic cells can regulate $T_{H17}$ cell development. Which of the following can induce $T_{H17}$ cell development?\n(A) High levels of IL-4, IL-6 & IL-17\n(B) High levels TGF-β, low levels of IL-6 & IL-23\n(C) High levels of TGF-β, IL-6 & IL-23\n(D) High levels of IL-12 & IL-18",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) High levels of IL-4, IL-6 & IL-17",
      "B": "(B) High levels TGF-β, low levels of IL-6 & IL-23",
      "C": "(C) High levels of TGF-β, IL-6 & IL-23",
      "D": "(D) High levels of IL-12 & IL-18"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "1. TGF-β、IL-6 和 IL-23 可以促使初始 CD4+ T細胞分化為 $T_{H17}$ 細胞;IFN-γ 和 IL-12 促使其分化為 $T_{H1}$ 細胞;有 IL-4 則分化為$T_{H2}$細胞;接收 IL-6 分化為 $T_{FH}$ 細胞; TGF-β和IL-2 則促使其成為 iTreg 細胞。\n［出自考古第1題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Memory T cells have distinct characteristics that contributes to their biology. Which of the following are the characteristics of memory T cells? (more than one answer)\n(A) Expressing Bcl-2 & CD45RO\n(B) Expressing early activation antigen CD69 and high levels of adhesion molecules CD44\n(C) Expressing CD122(part of IL-15 & IL-2 receptor) and CD25\n(D) Central memory T cells express CCR7 & CD62L",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Expressing Bcl-2 & CD45RO",
      "B": "(B) Expressing early activation antigen CD69 and high levels of adhesion molecules CD44",
      "C": "(C) Expressing CD122(part of IL-15 & IL-2 receptor) and CD25",
      "D": "(D) Central memory T cells express CCR7 & CD62L"
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "D"
    ],
    "explanation": "2. (A) Bcl-2為survival factor,在記憶性T細胞中表現較多,幫助細胞的存活; CD45RO 則在作用T細胞與記憶性T細胞的表面表現,調節 TCR signaling。\n(B) CD69 (early activation antigen)只在作用細胞(effector cell)表現;CD44 在作 用T細胞與記憶性T細胞都會表現,為細胞黏附分子(CAM)。\n(C) CD122 (part of IL-15 & IL-2 receptor)在作用T細胞與記憶性T細胞都會表 現;CD25(part of IL-2 receptor)則僅在作用 T細胞表現,但若記憶性T細胞 因抗原而再活化成為作用T細胞,則會再次表現出 CD25。\n記法:記憶性T細胞需要 IL-15, IL-7,作用 T細胞需要 IL-2。\n(D) CD62L 是 L-selectin,和CCR7一樣使中央記憶性T細胞(central memory T cell)回去停留在淋巴結等次級淋巴器官或周圍淋巴組織之中,此特徵類似初 始T細胞,而上述兩種蛋白質在初始T細胞和記憶性T細胞上表現量皆高,通 常以在記憶性T細胞表現量高,而在初始T細胞表現量低的 CD44 加以區分。\n［出自考古第2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Activated lymphocytes homing to a specific tissue are guided by the molecule expressed on their cell surface. Which of the following are characteristic of large intestine-homing lymphocytes? (more than one answer)\n(A) Express αEβ7\n(B) Express CCR10\n(C) Express CCR9\n(D) Express α4β7 adhesion molecule",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Express αEβ7",
      "B": "(B) Express CCR10",
      "C": "(C) Express CCR9",
      "D": "(D) Express α4β7 adhesion molecule"
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "D"
    ],
    "explanation": "3. T細胞在腸道被活化後會失去 L-selectin 並得到 CCR9(在小腸被活化)或CCR10 (在大腸被活化)和 α4:β7 integrin(和黏膜組織的血管內皮細胞上的 MAdCAM-1 結合移動)。T細胞在活化後到完全分化前的時候跟著淋巴一起流,跑到腸繫膜淋 巴結(mesenteric lymph node),然後流到胸管(thoracic duct)之後匯入左鎖骨下 靜脈,最後再從腸道的高內皮小靜脈(HEV)受到趨化素(chemokine)吸引跑出 來。這些回到腸道的作用T細胞可以在上皮層(epithelium)和固有層(lamina propria)這兩個區域找到,而預定要到上皮層的則會停止表現 α4:β7 integrin,改為 表現 αE:β7 integrin 以和上皮細胞的 E-cadherin 結合,並且以 CCR9 和小腸上皮細胞 的CCL25 結合或以 CCR10 和大腸上皮細胞的 CCL28 結合,藉此停留在上皮層。\n［出自考古第3題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement concerning effector CD4+ T cells are correct? (more than one answer)\n(A) IL-12 and IL-18 inhibit $T_{H1}$ cell differentiation\n(B) IL-10 and TGF-β inhibit $T_{H1}$ activation & g(後面題幹亡軼)\n(C) TGF-β and IL-6 induce $T_{H2}$ cell differentiation\n(D) IL-4 and IFN-γ inhibit $T_{H17}$ development\n(E) $T_{H1}$ cells produce IFN-γ, IL-10",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) IL-12 and IL-18 inhibit $T_{H1}$ cell differentiation",
      "B": "(B) IL-10 and TGF-β inhibit $T_{H1}$ activation & g(後面題幹亡軼)",
      "C": "(C) TGF-β and IL-6 induce $T_{H2}$ cell differentiation",
      "D": "(D) IL-4 and IFN-γ inhibit $T_{H17}$ development",
      "E": "(E) $T_{H1}$ cells produce IFN-γ, IL-10"
    },
    "answer": [
      "B",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "4. IL-12 會促使 CD4+ T細胞分化成為 $T_{H1}$ 細胞,IL-18也會促進 $T_{H1}$ 細胞的生成。 此外,受到 IL-12 (STAT4)以及 IL-18 訊號刺激的 $T_{H1}$ 細胞以及 ILC1 會產生 IFN-γ。\n$T_{reg}$ 細胞會分泌 TGF-β等免疫抑制的細胞介素以抑制 $T_{H1}$、$T_{H2}$ 反應,防止其過 度活化,以避免組織的過度受損;IL-10則會降低 $T_{H1}$ 細胞介素的表現。\n［出自考古第4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "The response of an immunized individual to the same antigen is different from a naive individual. How do their responses differ? (more than one answer)\n(A) Immunized individuals respond by producing higher affinity of antigen (看不到)\n(B) The frequency of antigen-specific B cells in immunized individual is about 102-103 higher than unimmunized naive individuals\n(C) (選項亡軼)\n(D) (選項亡軼)",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) Immunized individuals respond by producing higher affinity of antigen (看不到)",
      "B": "(B) The frequency of antigen-specific B cells in immunized individual is about 102-103 higher than unimmunized naive individuals",
      "C": "(C) (選項亡軼)",
      "D": "(D) (選項亡軼)"
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "B"
    ],
    "explanation": "5. (A)若選項結尾為 antigen-specific IgG 則正確,為antigen-specific IgM 則錯誤。\n(B) Frequency 從 1:104-1:105 增加到 1:102-1:103,課本敘述為 10 to 100-fold increase in the frequency,算對。\n［出自考古第5題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following molecules is recently found to be associated with severe drug hy-persensitivity reaction, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, to anti-seizure drug carbamazepine?\n(A) HLA\n(B) RORYT\n(C) CTLA4\n(D) FoxP-3\n(E) IFN-γ",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) HLA",
      "B": "(B) RORYT",
      "C": "(C) CTLA4",
      "D": "(D) FoxP-3",
      "E": "(E) IFN-γ"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "4. 由中研院陳垣崇院士研究發現中國、台灣及東南亞使用 carbamazepine 發生 Stevens-Johnson syndrome 的比例明顯較高的原因為 HLA-B*1502。(所以在使用 carbamazepine 前作的檢查是少數有健保補助的基因檢測)\n［出自考古第4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the target of cyclosporin A in inducing immunosuppression ef-fects on T cells?\n(A) NF-κB\n(B) NFAT\n(C) IL-2 receptor\n(D) IL-1 receptor\n(E) Toll like receptor (TLR)",
    "options": {
      "A": "(A) NF-κB",
      "B": "(B) NFAT",
      "C": "(C) IL-2 receptor",
      "D": "(D) IL-1 receptor",
      "E": "(E) Toll like receptor (TLR)"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "5. Cyclosporin and tacrolimus interfere with the translocation of nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT) to the nucleus by inhibiting calcineurin.\nBasiliximab 為 anti-CD25 antibody,會結合到高親和力的 IL-2 受體上以抑制 IL-2 訊號傳遞。但cyclosporin A 是藉由抑制轉錄因子 NFAT 而不表現 IL-2基因,與 IL-2 受體無關。\n［出自考古第5題］"
  }
]
